You know the feeling you get
when you learn something new
about a health problem
you’ve been trying to reverse?
Maybe high blood pressure,
diabetes, or heart disease.
Well, there’s nothing I like better
than bringing you the information
that will help you do just that.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we begin a new series
with the latest research
on a variety of topics.
First up, we look at
the benefits of vinegar
for blood sugar control
and polycystic ovary treatment.
The use of vinegar for weight
loss dates back to the 1700’s.
I did a whole chapter about
it in my book How Not to Diet
entitled Amping AMPK, the fat-
controller enzyme in the body,
which appears to be the
mechanism behind the multitude
of beneficial metabolic effects.
In my 21 tweaks to accelerate weight
loss I recommend 2 teaspoons
with every meal, which
is considered safe,
though it should be added
to food or diluted in water,
never consumed straight, and
diabetics should make sure
the vinegar doesn’t make
their blood sugars go too low.
But that’s one of
the benefits of vinegar,
blunting the blood sugar and
insulin spikes after a meal in both
healthy individuals and those with
blood sugar disorders like diabetes.
In a systematic review and meta-
analysis of interventional trials
of the effects of
vinegar consumption
on blood sugar control in
type 2 diabetes, vinegar improves
both short-term and longer-term
measures of blood sugar control
and as like a little
side bonus resulted in
a remarkable reduction in
cholesterol to boot.
And it didn’t seem to matter whether
it was apple cider vinegar or not.
All vinegar by definition has
the active ingredient, acetic acid.
So, what are the implications
for clinical practice?
Well, clinicians could
incorporate vinegar consumption
as part of their dietary advice
for patients with diabetes
with the caution that it
can work a little too good
and so you have to monitor closely
to make sure diabetic patients
aren’t overmedicated and
bottom out their sugars.
In my video on water purification,
I talked about this study
showing that the cheapest and best
way to disinfect your toothbrush
so you don’t have to keep
buying new ones maybe to soak it
for 10 minutes in 50%
white vinegar and water.
So what about a vinegar sock soak
for athlete’s foot or toenail fungus?
Foot soaks in half vinegar/half water
can help antifungals work better,
but inconvenience of tub
soaks limits compliance.
So, how about pouring vinegar
and water on the toes of your socks
and then just like putting your
feet up for a little while.
Not sure how that would
be any more convenient,
but seemed to work in
this clinician’s practice.
Instead of vinegar for
just an athlete’s foot,
what about vinegar
for the whole athlete?
“The Eﬀect of Vinegar
Supplementation on
High-Intensity
Cycling Performance.”
They randomized people to do
2 tablespoons of diluted vinegar,
or sugar, or both, or neither
and the vinegar did nothing.
Is there anything else
vinegar does help with?
The Intake of a Vinegar
Beverage Is Associated
with Restoration of
Ovulatory Function in Women
with Polycystic Ovary Syndrome.
For those of you unfamiliar,
PCOS is a major cause
of irregular menstruation,
and since insulin resistance
has been suggested to be
one of the causes of
polycystic ovaries,
and we know vinegar can
improve insulin resistance,
researchers decided to study
the effect of vinegar by giving
seven patients seeking a
non-pharmacological treatment
for PCOS, a beverage
containing a tablespoon
of apple cider vinegar
daily for a few months.
The insulin resistance
did improve in most,
but did their cycles return?
Yes, in 4 out of 7.
Before the study they were
either only having their period
every 50 days or so or none
at all or just not ovulating,
but most resumed within
40 days on the vinegar.
Now, this doesn’t prove anything,
but it’s at least sufficient
to indicate the possibility
that it may help.
And what’s the downside?
A tablespoon of vinegar would
cost less than 10 cents a day.
Just remember, never drink
vinegar straight, as it can cause
second degree caustic
burns down your throat.
Next up, we discover how coffee
and tea may impair iron absorption,
which may actually help explain
some of their benefits.
In my videos on tea, I caution
not to drink with meals,
because it can inhibit the absorption
of iron from foods
anywhere from 26 to 99 percent,
perhaps depending on the brewing time,
brand, or how strong it is.
What about the inhibition
of food iron absorption by coffee?
When I was first looking this up,
I ran across this study
on the effects of discontinuing
coffee intake
on the iron status
of Guatemalan toddlers.
I’m thinking they must be talking
about breastfeeding mothers
or something, but no, coffee
is one of the first liquids
given to infants in Guatemala.
I did not know that!
Anyway, the inhibition
of food iron absorption by coffee.
A cup of coffee reduced iron absorption
from a hamburger meal
by 39 percent, as opposed
to a 64 percent decrease with tea.
So, not as bad as tea,
but still significant blockage.
And just like with the tea,
the stronger the coffee,
the more iron absorption
was impeded.
In terms of timing, no decrease
in iron absorption occurred
when coffee was consumed
an hour before a meal,
but waiting an hour
after the meal
to drink the coffee
didn’t seem to help,
which can be probably
explained by the fact
that it may take
up to nearly two hours
to clear a meal
from the stomach;
so, starting an hour in,
the coffee can catch up
to the food.
Now, you can reverse
the effect of tea or coffee
by adding orange juice to a meal,
or even better an orange,
or any source
of vitamin C-rich food.
The vitamin C
boosts iron absorption,
which is good for people
who are borderline anemic,
but for many, the blockage
of iron absorption from coffee
may actually be a good thing.
Iron is a double-edged sword.
On the one hand, iron
is an essential element
vital for blood production.
On the other hand, iron
is a potent pro-oxidant.
So, maybe the reduced risk
of type 2 diabetes
associated with coffee consumption
is due to the inhibition
of iron absorption by coffee.
See, the risk of type 2 diabetes
increases with the increase
in the amount of ferritin
in your blood,
which is a measure
of your iron stores.
So, higher iron stores,
higher diabetes risk.
It’s the same thing with the risk
of gestational diabetes
during pregnancy.
So, you need to make sure
you’re getting enough iron,
but not building up
too much iron in your body.
How do we know
it’s cause and effect?
Because if you randomize diabetics
like old-fashioned bloodletting,
but instead of leeches,
they just donate blood
a couple times to lower
their iron stores,
and those in the blood donation group
had better blood sugar control,
better insulin secretion,
less insulin resistance.
Iron depletion improves
artery dysfunction
in type 2 diabetics as well.
It’s the same thing with gout.
Does inhibition of iron absorption
by coffee reduce
the risk of gout? Let’s find out.
Near-iron deﬁciency-induced
remission of gouty arthritis.
They took gout patients
and maintained their iron stores
at the lowest level possible
without causing anemia and…
gouty attacks markedly diminished
in every patient,
with effects ranging
from a complete remission
to a marked reduction of incidence
and severity of gouty attacks.
So, maybe that’s one reason
coffee consumption
is associated
with lower risk of gout.
It blocks some of the iron uptake.
Increasing evidence suggests
that iron is also involved
in multiple diseases of aging,
including Alzheimer's disease,
Parkinson’s disease,
and heart disease.
In terms of iron and Alzheimer’s,
they think it’s iron’s potential
to effectively “rust” brain tissue
by producing free radicals
that may cause neurodegeneration,
contributing to Alzheimer’s
disease pathology
at numerous levels, so much so
that there is interest
in trying to treat Alzheimer's disease
by targeting iron.
High body iron stores may also
be associated with shorter telomeres,
which is a biomarker
of biological aging.
And for those of you thinking,
well if I had high iron stores,
I’d probably know about it.
Only 5 percent of patients
with elevated iron report
ever being told by a doctor
that this was the case.
To prevent too much iron accumulation,
regularly drinking tea
with meals will do it,
found to decrease the amount
of bloodletting you
have to do for people
with a genetic iron overload disease.
But you’d want to do the opposite—
drink tea only apart from meals—
if you were at risk
for iron deficiency anemia.
Besides tea and coffee,
there are other beverages
that can block iron absorption.
Peppermint is right up there
with black tea,
chocolate milk would do it too,
and chamomile blocks iron
about in the same range as coffee.
So, if your iron stores are high,
these are great mealtime choices.
If you’re struggling
to get enough iron,
you wouldn’t want to regularly drink
these with meals.
We think it’s
the polyphenol phytonutrients.
So, what about herbs and spices?
They’re packed
with polyphenol goodness.
Now, this study was done
basically in a test tube,
not in real people,
but there is this case report
of iron deficiency anemia
due to high-dose turmeric.
A physician treated himself
for an osteoarthritis flare
with capsules of turmeric extract
and he was anemic,
couldn’t get his iron up
despite taking iron supplements.
But two weeks
after stopping the turmeric,
his blood count and iron levels
were all back to normal.
So, on one hand, those presenting
to doctor’s offices
with iron deficiency anemia
should be asked about supplement use;
at the same time,
the ability of turmeric
to glom on to intestinal iron
may lead to it being useful
in states of iron overload.
Finally today, we look at how
a single meal high in saturated fat
can impair cognition.
Having a high cholesterol level
in your early 40s is associated
with an increased risk of Alzheimer's
and vascular dementia decades later.
And your cholesterol doesn’t have to be
that high to increase dementia risk.
A 57 percent higher risk
of developing Alzheimer's
at a total cholesterol of 240
compared to under 200.
I’ve done a bunch of videos
talking about the clogging
of the cerebral arteries
inside of the brain
with the same atherosclerosis
that causes heart attacks and strokes,
choking off blood flow to the
memory centers in the brain.
This may be why higher
saturated fat intake was found
to be associated with the development
of worse global cognitive function
and memory decline, an apparent
acceleration of brain aging
as if you were six years older.
How can we cut down
on saturated fat?
By cutting down on cheese,
cake, ice cream, and chicken,
essentially the top
sources in the American diet,
but also pork, burgers,
and beef in general.
In my video on the role of glycotoxins
in cognitive decline,
I profiled this study, showing
that just five days of a high-fat,
low-carb diet impairs
energy metabolism in the heart
as well as cognitive function,
concluding such diets
are detrimental to the
heart and brain.
Now, they were thinking
the impaired energy production
may have accounted for the
brain dysfunction as well,
but high levels of dietary
glycotoxins, so-called AGE’s,
are also associated with
cognitive decline,
so we may want
to cut down our intake
of baked, broiled, or grilled meat,
chicken, or fish,
as well as certain
dairy products.
But there’s another possibility.
“Metabolic Endotoxemia:
A Potential Underlying Mechanism
of the Relationship
between Dietary Fat Intake
and Risk for Cognitive
Impairments.”
Endotoxins are highly
pro-inflammatory components
of certain types of
bacteria like E. coli
that are released
when bacteria die,
and can end up being absorbed
through our gut wall
and end up in the bloodstream,
resulting in what’s called endotoxemia.
The highest levels of these
endotoxins are found,
not surprisingly, in foods
like meat that are contaminated
with bacteria, both
red meat and white meat.
And having elevated levels of
endotoxin circulating
in your blood stream may be
detrimental for healthy aging,
associated with
a large range of diseases,
such as obesity, type 2 diabetes,
heart disease, and depression.
Put people on a high-fat,
low-carb diet for five days,
and endotoxin levels in the blood stream
roughly double.
Endotoxin levels before
and after a few days
on a high-fat diet.
In fact, even a single meal
can do it.
Give people some sausage
and egg McMuffins
with hash browns, and you
can get a significant increase
within hours after the meal.
How do we know it wasn’t the refined carbs
in the muffin or something?
Because the control meal
had a muffin too,
but lower fat
and no sausage and egg.
In fact, you can have people
chug straight sugar water
and no change in endotoxin levels,
whereas there was a big jump
within hours drinking straight cream,
which is pretty much straight fat.
And not just any kind of fat,
but mostly saturated fat.
A double-blind, randomized
crossover trial demonstrated
that a single meal
high in saturated fat
can impede attention
(meaning the cognitive ability
to distinguish target stimuli
from distractors in a computer game),
compared with an identical meal
high in the kind of fat
found in nuts, seeds,
and avocados.
And this cognitive deficit
was present five hours after the meal,
and who knows how much
longer after that.
There are two ways to cut down
on endotoxin bursts after meals.
One is to not eat so many
in the first place.
But if you do eat meat and dairy,
the addition of fiber-rich foods
can blunt the endotoxin surge.
Same sausage and
egg McMuffin endotoxin bomb
but with or without Fiber
One cereal,
which would be
like 30 grams of fiber,
and it seemed
to glom onto the endotoxins,
preventing the bump of endotoxemia
three hours after the meal.
The fiber also reduced
the oxidative stress,
the free radicals
generated by such a meal,
showing clearly that the addition of fiber
to the high-fat, high-calorie meal
had profound effects on metabolic
and inflammatory events
after the meal.
And over time, meal after meal,
this could have long-term implications.
Recent investigations reported
higher abundance of endotoxins
in the brains of patients
with Alzheimer’s disease
on autopsy—endotoxins building up
in the memory center of the brain,
the region of the brain
that develops the earliest
and most profound neuropathology
in Alzheimer’s.
Some advanced Alzheimer's patients
had up to a 26-fold increase
in endotoxin levels over
age-matched controls without dementia.
And where were the
endotoxins concentrated?
Smack dab in the middle
of the amyloid plaques,
a pathology characteristic
of Alzheimer's.
For these and other reasons,
proper nutrition has been proposed
as a promising
non-medical strategy
to prevent cognitive decline
and subsequent dementia.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and the “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Stay tuned for December 5, 2023
for the launch of my new one,
How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.